證人同埋陪同人士入場，唔該。
做咩啫？
首先歡迎誒各位出席調查港深港高速鐵路香港段建造工程議案嘅背景及原委專責委員會嘅第九次公開聆訊。
今日向專責委員會作證嘅證人係嘉科工程顧問有限公司項目總監。
Anthony John William King先生以及嘉科工程顧問有限公司項目經理吳少奇先生，歡迎兩位。
專責委員會已經同意Mr. King同埋吳先生嘅要求。
可有陪同人士出席呢個言訊？
Mr. King同埋吳先生嘅陪同人士係嘉科工程顧問有限公司嘅集團高級律師Miss Jennifer Kirkin。
噉啊！我想大家注意咧，就上述陪同Mr. King同吳先生出席嘅人士咧，係不可向專責委員會發言。
本席提醒證人。
本專責委員會係冇獲立法會授權行使《立法會權力及特權條例》第三百八十二章第九條一條嘅權力。
因為證人。
誒，因此咧，證人係唔受第三百八十二章賦予證人嘅特權所保障。
喺詢問過程裏邊，根據第三百八十二章第十八條嘅規定。
對專責委員會提出喺言訊主題上具關鍵性嘅問題，蓄意給予虛假嘅回答，或者向專責委員會提交虛假、失實、捏造或捏改嘅文件，而意圖欺騙專責委員會，即屬犯罪。
我相信證人係會真誠咁協助委員會嘅工作。
專責委員會已經制定本身嘅工作方式同埋程序，我請大家留意以下幾點。首先，第三百八十二章所定嘅議員特權咧，只係適用於言訊嘅過程。
所有議員，包括非專責委員會委員嘅議員，都應該避免喺言訊過程以外嘅場合發表同言訊有關嘅意見。
另外，我想借呢個機會提醒旁聽今日言訊嘅公眾人士同埋傳媒人士，喺言訊過程以外場合披露言訊。
中提供嘅正功咧，係唔受第三百八十二章所保障。
所以，如果有需要嘅話，各位人士同傳媒朋友咧，係應該就佢哋嘅法律責任，徵詢法律意見。
喺稍後嘅過程裏邊，我會要求證人就佢哋曾經向專責委員會提交嘅陳述書作出確認。
將陳述書納入成為專責委員會嘅證據，同埋上載喺立法會嘅網頁，公公眾查閲。
而家夠鐘，亦都有足夠嘅法定人數，我宣佈言訊開始。
嗱，Antony King先生同埋吳少奇先生，你哋曾經喺二零一五年十月二十日向專責委員會秘書共同提交一份證人陳述書。
即係專責委員會文件第W十三括弧C號。
嗱，阿Anthony King先生，你而家係咪正式向專責委員會出示該份證人陳述書作為證據？
yes。
吳少祺先生，你而家係咪正式向專責委員會出示該份該份啊證人陳述書作為證據？Yes。
啊！為咗方便列席嘅公眾人士同埋傳媒跟隨專責委員會嘅程序，我哋會應佢哋嘅要求，將閣下嘅陳述書向佢哋公開。你哋對剛才提交嘅陳述書有冇即時嘅補充？
no。
劉振，哦，OK，好。
噉我想提醒各位委員喺根據專責委員會工作方式同程序第十五段喺公開言訊裏邊，委員只應為確立同專責委員會嘅調查相關並屬於調查範圍內嘅事實而提問。
委員係唔應該喺呢個言訊裏邊發表意見或者係作出陳述。我會根據工作方式同埋程序第十六依段咧，決定某條問題或者某項證據係咪同專責委員會嘅職權範圍所在嘅調查相關，係屬於呢個調查範圍內嘅事。
而根據工作方式同程序第十六F段咧，委員係可以提出簡短嘅跟進問題，以圍繞原來嘅問題追問更詳細嘅答案，或者要求澄清所給予嘅答案。
而我作為主席有酌情權，決定某條問題係咪屬於跟進問題，以及應否容許委員提問該問題。
另外，每位委員嘅提問時限咧係啊十分鐘，包括證人嘅回應。委員係可以選擇向一位或者兩位證人提問。
噉就今日嘅言訊咧，我先向兩位證人啊提出第一條問題。
嗱，根據兩位嘅陳述書第十三段咧。
貴公司係受聘於路政署，出任路政署嘅監察同核證顧問，啊，佢哋嘅M and V Consultant。
噉就協助該處咧就高鐵香港段項目進行監察同埋核核證嘅工作。
咁喺陳述書第三、第四段表示咧，你哋兩位喺二零零九年係起咧就正式參與高鐵香港段項目嘅工作。我想請兩位向專責委員會簡述。
你哋以及貴公司喺二零零九年起就高鐵香港段項目嘅參與，唔該。
Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
We started in 2009 on the first stage of the M and V, which was the design and investigation stage.
And we were engaged by the highways department to assist them in their monitoring and verification role.
We.
put together a team to look at the quality, safety, programme and cost issues around the project through the design period.
and.
carry out a number of reviews of design documents.
preliminary preliminary design and detail design, we carried out some reviews of some.
tender documents.
We carried out audits.
on the work of the design consultants working with MTRCL.
We we were carrying out work with the buildings department where we had a team seconded to look at the designs submitted by MTRCL for for for the project. Sorry.
Miss King打斷你一陣，你正話講個team咧個編制有幾大嘅？
the the establishment of our team was about twenty two full time equivalents.
那means that we had some people full time and some people not full time, but but 22 full time equivalents, and we had access to about 30 experts on specific subjects within a normal high speed rail project。係好，請你繼續。
嗯。
Okay. So and and the the key to our work was that.
This is a very large project. There are enormous amount of
of documents.
和信息。
And so we could only approach this by sampling the documents.
and and we did this by carrying out a simple risk analysis of where the risks were likely to occur in the project, and based on that.
那 risk analysis。
which we carried out jointly with the highways department, we were able to focus on on the key areas where where risk may risk may occur.
The.
work that we did was.
All reported to the highways department in written reports.
by。
Written reports on the documents we reviewed.
monthly report to the highways department, and by presentation to the highways department, where we explained and discussed with them the issues that were occurring.
In in two thousand and ten, we were further asked to assist highways in the construction stage.
which is the stage that we're working on now, and we we went forward with a similar sized team, but instead of them all being design based, we have a monitoring team on site. We've continued with our work for the buildings department. We're continuing to review documents, but then largely documents generated.
由The Construction Contracts。
And again, we review documents and pass comments in writing to the Highways Department.
And we have a have a small team on site who are monitoring the site works. They, with the highways department, visit site once a month.
to look at specific things facilitated by MTRCL, we're continuing to carry out.
audits of MTRCL construction management teams at the working level for for each of the of the key contracts.
And we are.
working on specific items that arise from time to time.
and as well as that side which dealt with the programme, and the quality.
和安全 issues and construction issues. We have a team involved in.
Finances of the project, assisting highways department on a monthly basis, determine the the build up of costs as submitted by MTRCL.
你可唔可以講講你個人嘅參與係，自從二零零九年到而家係係點樣樣嘅？唔該。
Well, in two thousand and nine.
嗯。
I I was.
我唔係喺香港。
我我我visited Hong Kong.
嗯。
on a monthly basis.
and my main responsibility was for the audits.
But I, as deputy project director then, I was also responsible with the project director and the other deputy project director and the project manager for helping to guide the team in in the areas we should look at and and and how we should respond to highways department.
是。
requirements.
誒。
That has continued.
From two thousand and nine up until two thousand and fifteen.
where for various circumstances due to various circumstances, I became project director and since then since April of this year, I've been in Hong Kong full time.
during the build up to to
the current situat the current situation on site.
係，吳生，你有冇補充？啊，OK，Thank you，Chairman。啊。
I'm not going to repeat what Mr. King has mentioned about what our role, what our scope of work and how we carry our work. But as far as myself is concerned, I involved in the EXCEL project since two o nine and be.
The project manager for the monitoring verification consultancy services. Up till now, I'm still the project manager for the construction phase M and M works.
在邊一個phase啊？The MMV the second phase of the monitoring verification we call it MMV啊啊啊two。The first phase啊is the on the design and the啊啊investigation phase we call it MMV one。
Mr. Tang just mentioned in 202010， we were engaged on the second phase， on this construction monitoring on the construction works， which we call it in simple term we call it MV2，MV2。
Okay, so I I I was engaged as the project manager since two oh nine and up till now I'm still the project manager for the M M M V works.
啊！I the main point of key point of contact between our company and and and our client Harris Harris Department. And my main responsibility is to manage and coordinate the the works of our project team to ensure.
足夠資源，和也適當的資源被部署到這個項目適當的時間。
to make sure that we have a quality deliverable to our clients.
你可唔可以誒同呢個委員會講講咧？兩位啊，嚇誒。
你哋喺一個工作上咧參與度有冇遇到啲咩特別大嘅困難？你可唔可以同委員會分享一下咧？你哋工作上？
冇，無論係你個人又好，你貴公司又好。
I don't think we've we've met any difficulties.
Based on our expectation and our clients' expectation of what we were required to do.
係完全冇difficulties，係完全冇困難以上。
誒。
in in in carrying out our services.
在承攬出我們的服務。
no difficulties, no personal difficulties, as you can see from our from our statement.
at some stage, information was hard to obtain from from MTRCL.
但無困難度，with MTRCL in terms of the work we had to do. For example, our audits on site, our site visits and and and the monthly progress meetings that we held with MTRCL contract managers. 嗨，吳生。
啊，Well， generally we don't have too much difficulty on our works.
Occasionally, we may have faced with some difficulties in getting information from MTLCL, because we have a system of requesting document from the MTLCL via the share point system, which was established at the commencement of the of our work, and we make our request for the documents and.
MTLC generally forward all these document to us. Sometimes maybe take a little bit longer than than expected, but we do receive the document. But
In some of the sensitive document, like the overall master program, we may have difficulty obtain that instantly in first hand information. So that's why that strictly speaking, in term of difficulty, this may be one of the the area that we are facing.
會深深入。你可唔可以誒同我哋分享一下係邊一類型嘅資訊同埋文件係？Particular誒inform誒information誒relate to誒啊誒po誒the overall master program. Basically, keep asking for updating of the overall master program. We do receive誒。
contract呃po呃construction or contract programme for individual contracts. So we have we have a knowledge of the the progress of each individual contract and how the the delay of each individual contract impacting on the overall market interference, the addition contractor work or addition contract that.
That set the information that we sometime may not be having the first hand information.
盧偉國議員。
好，誒，多謝主席。
誒，我首先嘅問題咧都係跟進咧，嘉福公司同埋呢個港鐵公司喺呢個工程監督上嗰個溝通上嘅問題。
誒，正如頭先主席你誒問嘅問題方向一樣。
咁其實頭先就阿吳生都講到咧，就係話誒誒嗰個誒project programme嘅問題，或者亦都係喺陳續書嘅九十六段所提到咧，就係喺誒十一月誒唔係二零一一年六月咧就。
家科公司咧曾經係要求港鐵公司提供個overall project programme，咁但係當時咧係港鐵公司係提供唔到嘅，咁呢個係咪即係獨立專家小組報告？
誒三點一六段所指嘅綜合工程總綱計劃咧，即係integrated master program，即係話overall project program係咪即係等於integrated master program咧咁？
就同埋事後咧，其實就港鐵公司有冇係補充翻呢方面嘅資料咧？
就另一個咧，都係都可以講係相關嘅，都係一個溝通上嘅問題。就亦都係陳述書裏邊咧，一百三十六段咧就提過，就話咧二零一三年九月嘅時間咧，港鐵公司咧向路政署同埋誒嘉科公司咧提出局。
部通車方案。
係咪喺呢個時候？誒，你哋公司先至首次知道咧呢個局部通車嘅方案咧噉，同埋咧路政署有冇諮詢過兩位咧關於局部通車方案嘅可能性咧？
係Mr. King吳生。
In in answer to the first question.
The project master programme and the integrated master programme are the same thing.
And in terms of the MOR, that that that we had one presentation.
那係第一次， Jacobs 有知曉有個 MOR 提案喺度。
I I can't say any more because after that date we had no direct involvement in the MOR.
the the presentation, chairman, the presentation to us was on the I think remember correct is on the August two, one, three.
係咪？
所以那係第一次我們aware of the M.O.R.
係。
誒，我想跟進就係。
跟住就冇再就呢個M O L，即係局部通車方案咧，係作過任何嘅跟進或者討論嘅係嘛？
係兩位。
We had no further formal discussions on MOR.
With our client or with MTRC?
OK。
誒主席，我想再進一步問咧，就係誒前勞政處處長阿魏志誠先生咧，就喺喺我哋六月二號嘅言訊咧，就指出咧，就話整個項目咧，最後分成咧四十多份唔同嘅合約，每份嘅合約咧都有開工期。
但係，魏志瑩先生咁講嘅話，我覺得我哋詳細分析嘅時候，唔應該只睇完工期，仲要睇合約嘅開工期。如果開工期遲咗，而完工期咧又冇調整咧，換中期自然就少咗。
唔知兩位咧，有認唔認為咧，港鐵公司冇就延遲批出嘅工程合約調整完工期咧，係會造成多份合約嘅工期出現滯後嘅原因咧？
係兩位。
the the most significant delayed to award was contract 810A in WKT.
那 was finally awarded three months late, and we reported that to our client at the time as being a risk.
係。
啊！我想跟進問，吳生有冇補充？係你好，劉劉長劉長明。
呃。
咁亦提出咗。
問題，但係就港鐵公司就喺呢方面係冇作任何回應，或者係冇任何調整，係嘛？
Mr. King。
we raised we raised that issue in our monthly report to.
our client。
in in the in the vast quantity of other reports that that went through to MTRCL.
嗯。
and。
This is not the facts that I know.
This issue was probably raised, but we certainly raised the issue of a delayed award of 810A a number of times in the run-up to to the award of that contract.
因為它 was clearly it was clearly the largest and most difficult contract and and it was awarded last.
誒。
好，我主席誒，我想繼續問咧，就陳述書裏邊嘅第三十三段咧。
就提到就係誒貴公司咧會利用港鐵公司嘅項目綜合管理系統，即係PIMS去檢視咧同高鐵香港段項目嘅相關文件，而作監察嘅。
誒而韋正誠先生咧喺誒本年六月二號嘅言訊之後，亦都有補充到咧。
佢話監核顧問即係交科工程顧問公司，可以直接進入港鐵公司嘅系統，知識承建商嘅資料，包括承建商向港鐵公司提交嘅信件，但係咧就唔包括誒附件。咁如果係監核顧問咧，認為呢啲附件嘅內容咧係可以幫助去。
進行呢個監察工作咧，就可以透過行常嘅機制咧，經港鐵公司咧係索取承建商嘅相關附件嘅。
噉我哋想問咧，就誒唔知誒兩位啦，誒你嘅團隊咧想進入港鐵公司嘅項目綜合管理系統，即係PIMS嘅時候咧，有冇受到港鐵公司嘅乜嘢嘅限制嘅咧？
係，Mr. King。
Just a clarification. The the PIMS is is MTRCL's project management system. It's their procedures in carrying out their construction management.
And we we had access to the PIMS and to the revisions to the PIMS for our work to date. And in fact, we we reviewed the PIMS at the start of our assignment, and we review each of the PIMS as they're updated by MTRCL as they move forward.
唔差。
啊！
regarding the the access into the the system to obtain the information, I think Mr. Low just probably referring to the SharePoint system that we have that was set up at the start of our project. We do have access to to to the system to to.
to obtain or to view the document, whether online or to request for the documents. As I mentioned just now, we make the request based on our our risk approach on the risk items and and
classify what sort of document we would like to review, and then send our request to MTL Wire, our client, and
and then we will have we'll get the document afterwards.
啊，主席，我想進一步問咧就。
誒。
路政署嘅鐵路拓展處處長啊，陳志恩先生咧喺本年十月二十號嘅言訊裏邊咧，曾經指出過咧。佢話港鐵公司咧係冇制定一個綜合嘅工程總綱，但係咧我哋知道港鐵公司其實有一個工程總綱，有一個master plan。
然後咧，就賦予每個工程合約裏邊咧，都有好多本身嘅時間表。
誒。
唔知道兩位咧，對於呢個問題有咩睇法？港鐵公司咧是否欠缺一個綜合嘅工程總綱計劃，以致各方係冇辦法掌握咧邊啲合約對於項目嘅進攻日期咧係至為關鍵嘅咧？
係兩位。
Mr. King先啦，唔該。
I think I think in terms of master plan, you're referring to the master programme.
which is the timeline for the project.
MTRL did have a master programme. They had contract master programmes for every contract, which under the terms of the contracts were the programmes that were used in contractual terms.
That that that was converted into a project master programme, which also included the interface between the contracts and and through to the testing and commissioning, which was which was not necessarily contract based.
MTRCL。
certainly had that.
and。
誒。
To our knowledge, they used that in in terms of planning the work the works that were to come.
但那master program。
which we saw.
sometimes audits。
when it was tabled.
但，was never released to us.
for for reasons that MTRCL
嗯。
May may may tell you.
但。
The point about the master programme was, its criticality.
是基於，The critical path。
到 completion， and not necessarily the progress.
吳生，啊，Chairman，no more supplement。
四百個億。
其實即係以你哋誒公司喺呢個項目裏邊誒一個咁重要嘅工作。
就。
對於誒嗰個工程總工計劃咧，似乎你哋都唔能夠掌握到咧。其實會唔會影響咗你哋執行合約上你哋嘅職務？
Mr. King。
We requested the master programme because it would have assisted us in our work, as it would have assisted.
our client, the highways department.
But MTRCL were very transparent in their reporting of progress and target dates, and very transparent in their in in in their reporting of contract.
target dates。
and。
while it may while it may have have affected.
Our ability to understand when the completion date.
was as it was shifting, it it didn't it didn't prevent us from reporting on a regular basis that the project was late.
and that the delays were mounting, and that the delays.
were eventually going to affect the completion date of the project.
主席誒，綜合頭先嗰幾個問題嘅回應咧，我就想問兩位證人咧，會唔會感覺喺個工作上咧出現一種咧係？
只見樹木。
見唔到森林嘅狀況，即係話佢可能有啲細節咧，誒佢都掌握到，但係反而整體個計劃，整個森林佢哋睇唔到咧，有冇噉樣嘅感覺？係。
Mr. King。
Do you think you could ask that question again? Sorry.
嗯。
嗰個。
誒，再重複一次咧，誒。
或者用英文講咧。
From the response to the few questions have been asked.
嗯。
我有個印象，那。
嗯， in。
in the in your carrying out of your work, seems that you can see the trees, but unable to see the whole forest.
That means you may have the details about individual projects, individual programme, but the overall plan is not what you can master. What what the honourable W K Low was saying is that while you were praised.
of all the minute details of the development of projects.
但你 have missed the overall progress, the overall plan.
of the of the project, especially I think with regard to completion.
Thank you, Chairman. With respect, our role was to have a high-level view.
And from very early on in the project, we had an overview of the programme.
and that is why we reported consistently.
那個project was in delay due to the various component delays of the various contracts.
And if the delays continued and weren't recovered, there was going to be a risk to the end date of the project.
and as as and that reporting was consistent.
and as we moved into I believe 2012, we then made our own
simple analysis of what the delays meant in terms of completion date, and again that was reported to highways department on a on a regular basis.
啊，啊，吳生，你可唔可以補充？
誒，正如Mr. King just said。
Well, we have gathered information of all the progress of individual contract. From information that we receive, we made our simple analysis. As we said, we are on a high level. We don't have all the necessary information to carry out a detail.
Independent assessment of the likely completion day. We we could only do whatever we could based on the information information that we have in hand. With a simple estimation or analysis, we came up with a project delay early as early as in two two o one two.
and then we make our report report to our client, Irish Department.
That's I think.
overall，we don't see there's any a a problem with the
啊，with our work as far as啊。
on the detail of the of the project, or even on the as an overall view, overall view of the overall situation of the project.
好。
主席可唔可以再？
好，最後一條問題。最後一條好啊，誒。
我我想問下兩位咧，就係誒。
喺你哋。
提出咗你哋嘅報告，指出咗問題之後咧。
其實你哋覺得咧係唔係得到港鐵公司同埋路政處嘅誒重視，同埋咧係有真正咧係跟進呢啲問題嚇，即係佢哋兩方面有冇就你哋嘅意見，或者你指出咧係疑誤嘅情。
情況咧，佢哋做出應有嘅跟進咧。
Mr. King.
just one point of clarification.
Our relationship was with highways department. We we were assisting them in their M and V works. We had no direct relationship with MTRCL.
Except audits.
但無其他直接關係與MTRCL at all。
we op we operated at what has been called the third tier of the three tiers of of M and V.
And we were reporting to our client on a regular basis, and we attended briefing meetings with MTRCL on on the construction progress of con of contracts.
as well as the
extracts from the reports that we have in our statement.
We also presented.
Our.
findings on a monthly basis to RDO.
and that they took them forward.
但 in what form they took them forward and how those were discussed, we we we have no knowledge, no factual knowledge.
唔該。
下一位係胡志偉議員。
啊！唔知唔知吳生有冇？
好，吳生有冇補充？正話一條問題。No, Chairman。
胡志偉議員。
誒，多主席，聽聽咗係誒，涉及兩位同事嘅會議，我想。
即係。
搞清楚一點。
誒，即係有權力。
有渠道可以直接攞到所有嘅一啲你想知嘅係工程細節。
因為你哋可以係誒接觸到pins。
即係嗰個編嘅system裏邊。
個piece system係咪會讓你哋係攞到曬所有嘅工程嘅細節嘅資料？
但係你就攞唔到嗰個誒master program。
所以。
你只能夠係。
access到嘅係個工程嘅一啲即係好piece meals嘅處境，但係你睇唔到overall pictures，因為你掌握唔到個critical path to completion。我我想confirm呢一個state，我呢個噉嘅係。
誒，剛才頭先嘅聆聽咧，唔知有冇理解錯？剛才頭先啊，盧盧議員所問嘅嗰段説話嘅內容，我想問翻呢一點先。即係問題係你係咪好比較掌握嘅係嗰個別嘅工程？
個合約嘅嘅情況就係誒，反而就嗰個個總個總體嗰樣嘢係未未冇咁掌握，係咪冇一？因為你冇一個master plan，一個master plan。
誒一個綜合嘅一個一個。
啊！呢個綜合嘅工程進度表嚇。
Thank you, gentlemen. Just again, one clarification: the PIMS is a process for managing projects. The access to the documents was through a document management system called SharePoint, and it was through SharePoint that we could access.
Documents that were on SharePoint.
by requesting through highways department to MTRCL.
and。
We requested the documents.
That we needed, and there were thousands of documents on on on SharePoint. We had to be selective.
and so we selected documents to assist us in the work in the work that we were doing.
嗯，and we did not get。我諗Mr. King嗰個唔係問題，或者或者幫幫胡志偉員就將嗰個問題咧，將個breakdown。你有冇一個地鐵公港鐵公司嘅誒綜合嘅工程進度表？有master plan。
master program。
We did not receive a copy of the master programme in in the period leading up until April two hundred and one.
Four, two o o one, two two o one four，即係二零一四年之後，你就會攞到嗰個master program。
係，咁答咗你問題啦，都冇嚇，嗯。
我想請兩位可以解釋一下咧個，因為頭先我聽阿Mr. King講咧誒，你哋唔掌握critical critical path to competions嘅，可唔可講講畀我哋聽個critical path to competions係會對你喺成個工程嘅係評估裏邊工程進度評估裏邊有啲咩影響？
Mr. King。
We did not see MTRCLs.
Project Master Program。
given to us as a whole document that we could review.
它被表決於各種審計。
and so we could discuss it.
We。
could ascertain what the critical path was.
what what what were the final contracts to be finished and what were the elements of the final contracts that were to be finished that would impact the opening of the railway and and the opening of of WKT
And but what we couldn't do was ascertain the impacts of the change in delays to the projects in the changing changing to the critical path.
And again and again, we we reported that when we were reporting on the progress.
That was declared by MTRCL and that we had observed ourselves that while the reporting method that was being used for reporting delays was
fine， and it was accurate.
the the criticality of the critical path was the important thing.
我想問下Mr. King，咁因為攞唔到呢個critical power去做個independent assessment，你哋係有將呢個要求咧係同你個clients highways講咗。
有講過嘅。
有向highways request。
Full highways要求MTLC提供呢個係master programme或者critical path。你有冇你有冇經過誒路徑處理clients？
係要求地港鐵公司提供個master program。
We did.
係幾時係向呢個誒勞政處提出呢個要求？
第一次啦，嚇！
十二年。
It was certainly in the very early days of the project, and in fact, the.
There, there is a a paragraph in in our report which which specifically refers to the master program. I can't, I can't.
翻就得啦嘛！主席，可可唔可以噉樣樣咧？因為呢個都或者你你之後你提供書面提供畀我哋好唔好啊？呢個你第一次係向律政處提出啲要求。
呢個master program嘅要求好嘛？Yes，主席，我諗我想多少少知你唔止第一次，因為佢可能係重複係重複係向呢個highways係要求噉，但係我哋似乎聽落就係去到二零一四年嘅四月之後咧，誒，Jus及斯再加到嗰個master programs，咁所以我想即係由。
接及開始take up呢一個job開始，佢。
即係on and on去request for呢個master program嗰個情況咧，都有個彙報。
係，所以要求係咩話？即係個master programme，因為佢每一次都可能因為佢得唔到呢個master programme嘅時間，影響咗佢對成個工程進度嘅評估。係啊，當然噉，然後佢就好自然地就會請highways去即係去攞呢個文件啦。咁但係highways可能有處理或者冇處理啦。咁但係總會有個feedback翻過嚟㗎嘛。噉我想睇到。
呢一個噉嘅，即係。
responding嘅過程係。
誒。
Mr. King同埋吳生，你哋可唔可以提供？
翻嚟睇下可唔可以提供有關你哋向路你個client路政署要求攞呢個港鐵公司嘅master program嘅誒所有嘅要求啦，咁多年以嚟嚇嘅同埋佢嘅回應，路政署嘅回應，如果有嘅話，你可唔可以提供呢啲噉嘅資料？唔該。
Mr. Chairman.
Our reports and the work that we do is is the property of the highways department.
and therefore, any release of that documentation will have to come through them.
或者你向佢誒向佢哋要誒問一問佢哋好唔好啊？如果係咩，我哋會再。如果你係話，如果佢係唔畀你提供嘅話咧，噉你同到時你回覆翻我哋好唔好啊？
Yes, chairman。好嘛，唔該。Okay。
主席，我我想跟進第二個部分咧，就係誒。
site visit咧，我相信係成個監督工作裏邊一個幾重要嘅部分嘅。咁根據文件嘅係誒段落咧，就指出。
所有嘅西醫實質都要arrange或者assist by呢個MTRC。
我想問下一嗰個site visit咧，係咪每一次都係有個好specific嘅purpose，或者唔一定每一次啦，即係會經常都有呢個specific嘅purpose，佢為咗一個specific嘅questions咧去做site visit。
做呢個西區食嘅時間，誒係咪事先要同Highways咧係溝通咗？
去驗方fully驗方fully be highways有啲乜嘢specific嘅問題，想係透過呢個service即係found out。
噉。
而你去做survey visit嘅時間，因為要request MTRC去做assistance畀佢去進行survey visit。
需唔需要將你嗰個whistle嘅purpose都要inform咗MCRC先至可以做得到？
然後做完個survey之後，係唔係會有個full report、full findings，inform翻highways，inform你哋覺得應該有啲乜嘢嘅comments去處理你哋所希望能夠處理到嘅嘢？
誒嗰個specific嘅purpose嗰件事，你你可唔可以重複？你其實簡潔啲重複問你啊，我都唔係好明呢個。OK，其實我一連串咁行，我一步一步行咯，我主席會事。
嗯。
每一次嘅西visit。
係咪都係with specific嘅purpose？
YES或NO得㗎啦，係，Mr. King。
Chairman, I'll just have to explain the protocols behind the site visit. At the beginning of of our work.
高ways Department and MTRCL had agreed the protocols.
One of the issues was that our work shouldn't interrupt or interfere too much with MTRCL's work and site teams.
which is reasonable.
and therefore it was agreed that on a monthly basis we could visit the sites that we selected.
and。
which we agreed with highways department beforehand because they had a team of engineers themselves that were monitoring each of the each of the sites. We then put together a programme of visits.
We wouldn't visit every site every month. We'd visit the sites where we knew there were things of interest and issues that that we'd seen in the MTRCL reports and that we we knew about. And we we were specific about the site visits. And within the site visits, we told MTRCL.
what we would like to see in the site visits, and when the site visits were complete.
Sorry, and during the site visits, we we talked to the MTRCL site teams on on site. On on some, we were given a briefing before we went out to site on on progress and and what would be seen that day. And at the end of the site of each site visit, we prepared a report for the highways department, which.
They keep on record.
OK。
Mr. King其實答咗我嗰個長商，誒。
或者如果噉樣，我想請Mr. King，因為聽落嘅時候就每一次嘅西visit其實係為咗一啲即係。
誒對即刻嚟講有興趣嘅係內容同題目，我唔知可唔可以將誒survey set每一次個specific嘅內容同埋出嚟嘅findings同埋嗰個report同埋係highways嘅反應。
有一個嘅係。
即係summary畀我哋，仲係一個係資料咧。
你講係個審核嗰個audit嗰個過程嘅資料。I'm talking about a site visit。係頭先Mr. King講咗，每一個site visit佢都係要look into something interest，做嗰個嘅係monitoring或者去睇緊嗰個嗰個工作嘅。係，誒係Mr. King啊，吳生可唔可以提供噉嘅資料？
係喎。
Chairman, similar to my previous answer, all those reports were produced in confidence for our client, and and it would be up to our client to release them.
或者你向話同路政署好似上次咁啦，同路政署提出話，我哋委員會有專責委員會有噉嘅要求，如果到佢係唔同意你誒？
你提供啲噉嘅資料嘅話，你同我哋講翻好唔好啊？書面上，唔該。
多謝我仲想有，我想問下咧，誒，即及喺嗰個project control team上邊project control group，信唔住，因為嗰牽涉到就係誒M T L C去提供一啲誒。
即係追趕落後嘅係工具。
嘅時候，即係所謂嘅係誒誒delay。
did they catch up嗰個remedies？
我想問下，即係喺呢個group水邊嗰個角色。
有關喺佢哋地鐵公司提出，港鐵公司提出嘅誒誒delay recovery measures裏邊嘅，你哋有冇參與喺啲喺呢個？
程序裏邊，你哋有冇參與？
We were involved in the.
process for delay recovery measures in that we reviewed.
The P.C.G. papers.
That were submitted to the P.C.G. meeting and made comments to highways department.
on on on those on those papers.
we didn't we we didn't.
attend the P.C.G. meetings ourselves.
烏智威。
誒highways喺二零一二年嘅時間咧，就receive係咪喺二零一二年嘅時候先至開始receive到誒？你哋公司指出。
M.T.L.C.所作嘅誒delay recovery measures咧，係冇乜實際成效。
我想confirm個date，Mr. King。
I think as a as a preamble to that.
所有嘅 delay recovery measures that were proposed.
were at the time proposed in good faith.
as being.
items that would improve.
The out-turn of the project.
We reported.
at certain stages, that despite the implementation of delay recovery measures, the programmes were still slipping.
係。
We're still slipping.
我誒你答完啦，係咪啊？先講啲問題。
主席，因為呢個係佢statement上面講嘅，即係喺二零一二年嘅時候咧，誒，佢係指出。
Delay recovery measures一個實際成效咧係存疑嘅。
噉我想問清楚就係，Highway係咪喺嗰個時間先第一次知道呢一個信息，同埋就係Highway嘅反應。
Mr. King.
yes, yeah, I'm I'm just thinking. I'm not. I don't know whether that was the first time the highways department, in this statement, that is the first time we reported it. We we probably reported it at other times.
The fact that although there had been delay recovery measures implemented, the programme was still slipping.
Now whether whether whether that statement was specifically to a specific delay recovery measure or whether it was a generality of of the programme slipping even though delay recovery measures had been implemented, I I I I can't say for a fact.係，我想問一問就係呢番跟進同一個方向嘅問題就。
係。
當時我大家都清楚，Jacob喺二零一二年已經係向政署提出話有嗰個滯後嘅情況開始出現。咁一路到二零一三年底嗰陣時咧，我講緊係即係如果係唔做嘢嘅話咧，就應該有成十一個月嘅。
有十一個月嘅一個滯後嘅情況，咁其實你由開始一路佢一路係用好多D R M去去嘗試去去挽救個情況個情個情形啦。咁但係一路都唔成功啊。噉你一睇到嗰個係嗰個係滯後嘅情況越嚟越大嘅話，噉你係同。
有冇畀啲咩任何意見畀咧路政署咧？即係你係見到開始細細哋噉，而家慢慢越嚟越大嘅嗰個嗰個滯後情況，噉你係點樣處理咧？同路政署方面？
Chairman, we we our role was to observe and to review, and to report.
And we reported to the highways department.
through our monthly reports.
and at monthly meetings and through our review reports, and we reported.
The delays.
The escalating delays, and then some assessment of what those delays would mean for the end date of the project.
We, as I said, we operated directly with highways department. Any discussions that the highways department had with others, I have no knowledge of.
誒以以你嗰個專業意見，因為佢有個係誒目標一個係完工程完成嘅日子嘅，就係應該係二零一五年嘅八月。
咁當時你喺二零一三年根據你哋嘅報告咧，就應該又有十三個月嘅滯後，誒十十一個月嘅滯後嘅情況嘅。噉你認為係喺呢個由？
一三年嘅十一月至到一五年嘅八月之間，係追回呢個十一個月嘅滯後情況，你覺得係認為，即係以你嘅專業，即係JAG嘅專業判斷，係冇係咪一個可行嘅做法？
With respect, Chairman.
I'm not sure I'm here to give an expert opinion.
At the time that the delays were occurring, we reported the delays.
And we quantified the delays, and we pointed out that if the delays weren't resolved, what the impact would be on the completion date.
明白噉，我我withdraw翻我嘅問題啊，副主委員。主席其實誒，我一路未聽到個答案，就係我想問：當家科係report咗呢一個即係delay嘅情況，我想聽highways嘅response to誒家科，同埋佢有冇任何instructions畀家科。
去即係跟進嗰件事。
Mr. King。
we we were in.
dialogue with the highways department at the meetings, we we discussed the seriousness of of the delay.
and.
We continued doing the work that we'd been doing to to look at the the key critical activities, and to continue reporting to the highways department.
所以你 don't，你 do not receive any comments or instructions from the highway departments。
on the delay of the project.
There was plenty of discussion and comments by the highways department. The whole project team were concerned about about the delay.
但係，我唔，我唔 recall， personally， whether we received a written instruction to do something.
但交通部和我們和MTRC都完全清楚，有延誤。
好。
下一位係田北辰二。
啊。
Mr. King。
啊！
The contract that you awarded by the government was close to about one hundred million dollars.
The contract that government awarded you was it close to 100 million Hong Kong dollars?
八十五萬。
Okay，close to 100 million，85。
And that's all taxpayers' money.
The nature of the contract that you sign with government.
我係 getting very curious now. Was it basically to answer each and every question when government ask, and if they don't ask?
主動 volunteer。
或，有冇個 general spirit？
to ensure that the contract.
was completed on time, and there was no cost overrun.
How would you conceive of the nature of that 85 Hong Kong dollar million dollar contract?
啊，Mr. King。
I'm not sure. I'm not sure exactly what your question is. Are you?
what's the purpose of that contract that that that that the government awarded you?
MTRCL were, if if I can put it into context, MTRCL were awarded.
the job of delivering.
The XRL project.
because of their track record and history of delivering similar projects.
It was done under a new form of contract.
for Hong Kong。
嗯，一個所謂的 concession。
arrangement with an entrustment agreement.
That we that we all know. My question is the contract government awarded you.
And the government were what were you supposed to do? The government were carrying out M and V services, and we were assisting the government in carrying out those services to review the work of MTRCL to.
assess whether they were delivering the project in in accordance with their processes.
and and that they were complying with good practice in safety and quality and okay so strictly giving advice.
Not to use your best endeavour to advise government, to work with MPR, to make sure that the project was completed on time. Right, there's a big difference.
I'm sure. I'm sure. Would you simply give advice? Sorry，第八十二，你可唔可以畀佢答答啊？你問咗問題。
Please answer the question, please, Mr. King.
The spirit. I'm asking about your understanding of the spirit of the country.
The spirit of the contract.
was us working with highways department.
whose main endeavour was to ensure that the project was delivered on time.
但係，delivery of the project was in the hands of MTRCL.
great great great， so your understanding is that the spirit of the contract is to work.
With MPR through government to ensure that the project was completed on time. Okay, now.
If that's the case, then I like to know.
The first time you attended this so-called PSC meeting.
was in.
February two thousand and fifteen, correct?
correct. prior to that.
You had never attended.
The PSC meeting.
which is actually.
very very crucial, because that's a direct interaction between government and MTR, where.
everything and anything， would be asked。
answered.
Okay.
所以，我的問題，然後變成。
你簽個contract。
with eighty five million dollars taxpayers' money with the government, and you knew perfectly well that your main job is to help.
ensure that it's completed on time, but you weren't even invited to the PSC meeting until all hell broke loose.
In.
二零一四。
啊！
你 accept that？ did you fight for？
attendance at these meetings.
Did you actually ever tell government that if we are not allowed to attend these meetings, there's no way I can do my job?
你 know， I I have to resign from my contract。 Do you feel attending that is critical for you to really understand this whole thing， rather than keep reading papers and papers and charts and charts？係，Mr. Mr. King，真係答係，你覺得。
係出席呢啲會議係咪重要咧？
就係淨係即係唔係淨係睇文件，亦直情係出席會議係會係對你工作嚟講係好重要。
the the。
The protocols and and the methodology under which we carried out our work was as directed by our client. Our client required us to support them in in the work that we did.
and we were not invited to.
The PSC meetings. Did you ask to be invited?
我唔記，得我唔係喺度，全部時間。
係阿吳生，你哋有冇要求過咧？呢間公司收咗八千五百萬立場嘅錢啊！會點不順意，或者等佢答一答先好嘛？我想我想問埋先好嘛？而而家我問緊嘢，OK？
你收咗八千八萬納税人嘅錢，你承認你主要嘅精神係令到盡你嘅能力，令到呢個誒項目可以如期完成。
但係佢冇邀請你出席呢個會。
噉你有冇強烈要求？
吳生。
啊！
啊， Chairman。
啊！一啲嘢，開發完盤。
Thus, our main role is to monitor the and carry the MMV services to ensure that MTLC are carrying out their work in accordance with their project management system and in accordance with the engagement agreements.
啊！
We are a lot obliged to our.
for the.
啊！
the the the problem that arise during the course of the construction that cause the delay.
as far as I recall, the protocol for our monitoring system was set up at the start of our services, and we were directed by our clients to carry out the works in accordance with the brief that we are。主席，我時間有限，我個問題好簡單啫，你。
你有冇強力要求？噉啊，有定有或者冇啫。
有冇要求咧？唔使話簡簡潔啲答。咁簡單嘅問題。
We don't recall we have made such a request for attending the PSC，但係我哋可以check，但係我唔recall。
吳生，你即係話畀我聽，你接受咗個。
噉嘅公誒一個噉嘅合約，你亦都明白你主要嘅目的。
個使命係要令到佢盡量如期可以完工，但係呢個咁緊要嘅會。
因為你係透過呢啲會，你先知道廣鐵嗰啲D R M啊。
係得定唔得㗎嘛？又或者佢有冇D R M啊嘛？甚至乎你可以喺度會度問佢critical part㗎。你冇master project program，你都可以喺P S C度問佢個critical part㗎嘛？
係咪？但係你從來冇出席過，直至去到一五年嘅二月。
噉你？
你你點可能履行你嘅職責？噉你啲advice咪全部係？
港鐵話幾多畀你聽，你就悲喪嗰樣嘢。
你嘅責任要喺BSC嗰度質疑港鐵㗎嘛？
啊！咁點解你會真唔記得你有冇要求出席呢個會咧？
Chairman，啊。
係，啲啲啲。
Well, we have this three tiers system. The protocol set up at this with this three tier system, we.
We were.
directed by our client because at each tier we have different people and we are assisting the highways department in the M and V works and then our clients they have also have a team of professional engineer who will be also sitting in this second level and the third and the third highest level meeting.
up to the directors level, so all our reporting is all in accordance with what we are asked to do, and
We all you as the engineer from the from the highest department. We also we will bring forward this our comment or our our concern to the second level or even to the highest level to MTLCL and最簡單嚟講，你唔記得你有冇要求出席呢個會議係嘛？
你唔記得？No，我個問題唔係佢有冇請你啊。
我嘅問題係你收咗政府一個簽咗個合約，你都有一個即係除咗商業啊，你都有一個責任嘅。呢啲係公堂嚟㗎，你睇唔過眼都可以出下聲㗎。佢冇請你，咁如果佢咩文件都唔畀你，噉你係咪咩都唔問啊？
都唔會㗎，係嘛？Of course，係咯。竟然成個過程八千五百萬嘅公堂嘅一個合約，你開聲要求話喂路政署，你真係要我幫到你，我要真係出席呢個會議問下嘢嘅。如果唔係，我就畀港鐵同埋啲民建
牽著地址走嘅咯喎，噉佢一味話信我啦，信我啦，噉我就要信嘅咯喎。
你因為你一齣席咗會議，你就知道佢啲DLM得唔得㗎啦嘛？
點解你會得連噉樣樣去問都唔問呢？
好啦，咁既然你承認啦，你唔記得仲有冇問啊？噉你今日睇翻轉頭，你覺唔覺得你哋好失職咧？
識傾或者唔生。
幾多個question？幾多個question？
問個question about。
sorry what was the what was the question again?
吳生，你答唔到我啊！
我唔想再翻譯啦，我其實可以英文問嘅。吳生，你答唔答到我？你覺唔覺得你有冇失職？啊，I I don't think we have。
啊啊！
Well, we follow all all what we are asked to do, and we don't. I don't think we have a.
冇任何 mistake on as far as we're concerned.
噉你原本話係想盡你嘅能力令到呢個工程完成，但係最緊要嘅會你冇去開，因為人哋冇邀請你，你連自己有冇要求都唔記得，噉你身為一個顧問。
噉我都覺得，我都有啲質疑。
你專業方便喎，真係。
因為呢啲係公堂嚟㗎嘛，係咪？
誒，咁噉，咪咪。
Yes, please. I understand that. May I just answer that?
MTRCL were required to ensure the project was delivered.
The highways department were monitoring what they were doing, but the responsibility for delivering the project was MTRCL, and we were assisting the highways department. The highways department set out certain protocols.
With some agree with MTRCL about meetings and site visits and various other things.
and we followed those protocols and we reported consistently from the information we had about.
The status of the project.
what was happening on the project and the delays and the consequence of the delays, and so it was absolutely clear to to everybody our view on the state of the project from 2011 up until 2014.
In November of 2013.
Alright, one month before December, when you declared that project eight ten A and B were fifty three weeks behind in November two thousand and thirteen, do you still believe that any kind of DRM can salvage the situation?
MTRCL were reporting that, despite the delays, they could recover. I see, and you tend to give them the benefit of the doubt, just like the government. We were not in a position to give them the benefit of the doubt. We reported what we saw, and what we read in the in the reports, and made our assessment and reported to government. And your report to government.
In November of 2013, was that you do not believe it can be completed on time?
或那，subject to the effectiveness of the DRM， it could be completed on time. What exactly was your advice to government?
在November of 2013.
專題制。
Because even that meeting，我唔係，我畀你答一答呢。No，we've，we've，we，we，have。
subsequently seen the events that led up the last quarter of two thousand and thirteen we were not at any of those meetings we weren't appraised of any of those meetings we were continuing with our work on site in in monitoring the contract programmes and and and the work that was being done on site okay well Highland.
田北辰議員，一其實田北辰議員咧係係誒提出咗一個比較重要嘅。
一個問題，我都想藉呢個機會咧，係同呢個專責委員會咧，係澄清呢個問題，就係有關你哋嘅工作。
因為我之前我聽咧，你哋係一個monitoring and verification consultants嗱，我。
特別係強調一個consultant，需要一個顧問嚇。
咁同埋，你哋係又話有個職責係去確保呢個係嗰個誒呢個工程咧係如期噉樣喺嗰個目標誒完工時間嗰度完工。
咁但係你正話答嘅問題，田北辰議員嘅問題咧，似乎嚟講到咧，你嘅角色係完全被動嘅，你係只係咧就係話踢一踢一腳就喐一喐，踢一腳喐一喐，係完全一個被動一個角色嚟嘅，就完全冇一個主動嘅角色扮演一個主動嘅角色，即係你係完全。
係唔畀意見嘅，即係路政署叫你做乜你就做乜啊。叫你做誒audit你就做audit，叫你做呢樣做A做A做B就做B，但係完全係冇一個主動向呢個路政署你個client提供一個專業意見嘅一個角色嘅。我噉樣嘅理解啱唔？
啱咧？究竟係邊一個係咧？你係最初嗰個同最初個你話係要確保啊，幫勞政署確保呢個目標、呢個員員工時間，同埋係一個consultant。但係似乎你而家同田北田北辰議員講嘅嘢咧，係完全唔係一個consultant嘅角色，一個mechanic嘅角色。
啊！請，我想你誒答回答畀個問題，Mr. King同埋阿吳生都係，所以我想搞清楚你哋個role係咩？究竟係咩嘢？
議員。
The responsibility.
and excuse me if I go back over over this, the responsibility for for delivering the project on time was with MTRCL.
Highways Department were monitoring their work and we were assisting them in the monitoring.
We reported.
Exactly， what we had seen by reviews and site visits.
And we made we gave advice in our reporting and at our progress meetings about the status of the project and what would happen if the if the project continued in in the path that it was going.
And that that so it wasn't a passive role. It it was proactive in terms of finding the information, sorting the information and presenting it to our client.
唔深。
其實。
誒老毛十幾蚊。
主席啊，主席，但係佢會都冇去開，佢憑咩資格話佢？佢講咗佢冇開呢啲會，佢又好可能係冇要求開呢啲會，點啊？唔該，翻個威爾。
主席，唔該，主席。誒，嘉科工程顧問雖然係政府聘請嘅獨立顧問公司，但係咧，我見到過去你哋提好多嘅建議，好似都冇得到政府同埋港鐵嘅重視嘅。咁所以，我哋先至質疑嗰個監察機制係咪真係起到作用？主席，我有四個問題想問。
想問啊顧問公司嘅，就係根據路政署署長劉瓜劉家強先生，佢喺六月九號提交畀我哋呢個專責委員會嘅補充資料，即係文件嘅編號G九嘅附件二咧，就話你哋獨立顧問曾經係檢視過港鐵地盤勘測同埋個岩土報告，亦都喺。
二零一零年嘅一月十二號，係去信過畀港鐵，就研討報告提出咗有三個關鍵嘅意見，嚇三個關鍵嘅意見。我想請問顧問公司，你哋提呢三個關鍵意見，到底指嘅係乜嘢？而呢三個關鍵嘅意見，根據你哋嘅。
理解係咪構成咗日後工程延誤嘅因素？
港鐵同埋政府咧，有冇正視到你哋呢三個嘅意見咧？係。
Mr. King.
Sorry, could you repeat the document number?
好啊，係文件編號G九嘅附件二。
嚇，路政署署長劉家強先生喺六月九號提交畀我哋立法會呢個專責委員會，係補充資料嚟嘅，係。
係關於呢個地盤勘測。
同埋岩土嘅報告。
I'm not.
I'm not sure if we've got that with us.
William係唔生係咪啊？
sorry，你係咪William係咪嚟啊？請問嚇，係。
係你嘅一封信，喺一二零一零年一月十二號畀勞政處嘅一封信，係英文嘅。
你 sweep到幾耐先見啊？
你哋講嘅critical observation。
可能是。
Sorry，啊，Mr. Fan，can you repeat the paragraph that you are referring to？哦，主要係一月十二號嗰封信係你哋寫畀港鐵嘅係。
yes.
我哋打開嘅，嗱，左耳部。
我哋寫啲。
Our letter is to highways department.
你哋係咪係講到話係有三個關鍵嘅意見，就嗰個即係誒檢視港鐵嗰個地盤勘測同埋岩土嘅報告㗎嘛？係。
請問你哋揾唔揾到嗰封信喺邊度？如果唔係主席，使唔使容後？因為我哋仲有第二節嘅，一係就我。
係問第啲問題先係，或者第問題啲問題先。我唔想唔想阻大家係好。第二個問題就係路政處處長喺上一次嚟我哋喺度言訊嗰陣時咧，就話路政處喺誒監核港鐵嘅工程進度嗰陣時咧，一直有一個判斷。佢哋嘅判斷就話工程滯後就唔等於最終係會有。
有疑誤嘅，我當然唔認同佢呢個判斷啦。其中顧問公司就喺二零一三年嘅七月就已經，你哋估計咧高鐵完工嘅日期咧可能延遲差唔多整整十一個月，而顧問公司喺陳述書裏邊第九十二段嘅附表裏邊咧，亦都係。
講咗咧，二零一三年嘅七月嘅每個月嘅進度報告裏邊咧，你哋確實有向路政署提出延誤十一個月嘅呢個估計。但係路政署署長喺嚟我哋呢個言訊嗰陣時咧，就話獨立顧問即係你哋呢十一個月嘅估算係建基於一個嘅基礎。個基礎係咩咧？就係港鐵。
如果完全唔採取任何追回進度措施，先至有呢個十一個月嘅估算噉。路政署嗰陣時做咩咧？佢就話選擇信任港鐵，所以就冇聽到你哋講即係呢個獨立顧問。你哋提出呢個嘅誒警告又好誒温馨提示又好，我想請問顧問公司，你哋。
到底認唔認同路政處處長嗰個嘅睇法？其實你哋當其時提出嗰個十十一個月嘅延遲嘅話，其實係咪有考慮到港鐵採取追回進度措施嘅影響嘅？係。
Mr. King.
the the。
11個月 delay was was our assessment based on the information we had from MTRCL, which we reported to highways department.
and。
That was that was a raw.
Calculation based on the situation at the time.
It did not consider the impact of any future DRMs or any DRMs that were in the pipeline. It was a straight interpolation of the current delay to the end of the project.
嗯嗯。
好明白，好噉。主席，我誒第三個問題就係港鐵行政總裁上一次嚟到我哋呢度言訊嗰陣時，承認咧就話工程嘅前期工作緊縮嘅準備時間咧，所以咧就令到有三份嘅合約八一零A、八一零B、八一一A三項涉及新。
西九總站嗰個嘅合約咧，就出即係要做多次嘅修訂。嗰個修訂嘅次數係多得驚人嘅。對我嚟講，八一零A嘅合約咧，就去到二零一三年，即係幾年前六月咧，就已經有一萬三千五百一十三次嘅修訂。
咁根據顧問公司你哋掌握嘅資料咧，呢啲合約嘅修訂到底可唔可以避免嘅咧？例如，如果港鐵去有合理嘅時間係去做一啲前期嘅準備工作嘅話，係咪就有機會唔需要有咁多數量嘅呢個嘅合約嘅修訂咧？而呢啲嘅修訂對？
高鐵工程嘅進度嚟講，係咪就真係好似港鐵佢多次強調，呢啲係一啲細微細眼嘅修訂，唔係即係令到嗰個工程嚇，因為有大量呢啲嘅修訂係出現咗疑誤嘅咧？
十K。
I'm I'm not sure.
我可以 answer that。
question。
except to say that on major construction projects.
most drawings get revised a number of times from preliminary design through detail design and then when you get to site and site conditions are understood.
Apart from that, I can't answer the specific question that you raised.
唔嘥噉嘅補充。
no，German。但係根據你哋嘅專業判斷，你哋過去嘅經驗嗱，我係講緊八一零A、八一零B、八一一A噉啊。港鐵誒就唔願意透露裏邊啲嘅細節，我係只係講話其中一份嘅合約喺兩年前嘅年中嗰陣時已經有成萬三次嘅一萬三千次嘅修訂，呢個係咪一個？
常態係咪一個正常嘅咧？係係，我哋知係會有修訂嘅出現，但係嗰個次數係多得好緊要。
三份合約裏邊，其中一份喺兩年前已經有一萬三千次嘅修訂。
啊，Miss King或者吳生德。
Apart from what I said in my earlier earlier answer, I can't make a judgement on that those thirteen thousand revisions.
噉你能唔能夠評論呢啲嘅修訂嘅次數咁多係有機會會導致嗰個工程嘅延誤咧？係。
又或者係滯後咧，係。
你哋做唔做到呢個判斷咧？
我唔係，
I can't say we we we we did know that there were an enormous number of drawings.
on this contract.
WKT。
and that those drawings were being revised as as the work progressed in the early stages. I can't make a comment on that number。唔，我唔係要求你誒，你你誒評評論呢件事，我係話你知唔知道呢啲噉嘅修訂嘅存在，一萬三千幾條修訂。
Personally, personally, I can't say that I was aware of the thirteen thousand revisions。係阿吳生咧。
呃，Well， we know there are changes in the design during the construction stage. But we don't know. Sorry, my question was specific. We don't know the exact number. Are we aware? Are we not aware? Well, we don't know. We are not aware of the thirteen thousand numbers. Okay. But we only aware of the total. They are. 佢哋唔知道有噉嘅數字。明白。多謝主席協助。咁誒就。
頭先我第一條，我可唔可以第一第二輪嗰陣時請佢哋嗰陣時先答我，因為佢哋要翻查文件啊嘛。關於個三個critical observation嗰度係得唔得㗎？係。
係，識傾或者唔生都得。
We only have the letter that quoting that we have made free critical observation in our review, but we don't have the attachment with this with the letter. That's why we have low knowledge of which free critical observation that we made at the moment.主席，我我揾出嚟畀佢哋啦。係好，我喺第二輪。
正話嗰你嗰個問題，需唔需要跟進翻？要啊要，我我就係話能唔能夠喺第二節嗰陣時，我跟進翻。哦，第二節跟進翻，O.K.
誒或者我哋係誒有十五分鐘嘅或者十分鐘嘅嘅小休好唔好啊？十分鐘。
噉就應該係誒搭嗰個鐘嘅搭三啦，好嘛？搭三。OK。
冇十五分鐘。